all
right hello
everyone coort 5 it's our first
discussion on chapter 4
so does anyone want to give just
any thought on four
overall just any any aspect of what they
expected or got from it or however far
they got or some section that was
just interesting to
them I have a
question
um
so one kind of generative model that I
am familiar with is um one way of
representing a gener model is using
markup decision process or partially
observable Mar markup decision
process uh this is for
discreet
um the discreete case of generative
modeling I'm
wondering what else what other what are
other very popular or
common uh structures that are used to uh
write down or Express generative
models anyone want to give a
thought
I would say one alternative way to write
down parts of generative models is the
continuous time but are you asking is
there another way to represent discrete
time generative
models other than with a
PDP right to begin with because of
course there's the the whole
other uh area of continuous time
but um there's one important aspects to
the
whole um question
of
um of basian inference which
is or some some agent some organism
that's implementing basian inference is
how does it uh not only learn the
parameters of a generative model but how
does it also learn the structure of that
model um and
this is connected for example to
questions about nature versus nurture
and and uh development in in humans or
animals like what are the um the initial
conditions what kind of um either
inductive priers or like um structure
biases doeses our neural
architecture uh provide us with from the
very beginning
and whatever it doesn't provide us with
how how do
we um figure out what kinds of structure
is appropriate for for
modeling a particular
domain all you have any
thoughts
uh well first of all uh about the
initial uh states of any system uh that
I mean it it doesn't always um in active
inference modeling we don't we don't
always assume U any agent like tabul
laasa like I mean we don't always begin
from scratch so uh in most cases we
necessarily impose some initial
conditions uh in order to make it more
efficient to model the exact behavior of
or phenomenon of interest uh because
otherwise we won't be able to
um to model the whole process I mean all
the emergent properties that um the
agent have acquired the the agents have
acquired through their lifespan uh so it
is uh it wouldn't be feasible to try to
um put everything in in such an
encapsulated form of um generative model
in order to Encompass uh the agents uh
entire u i mean experience and lifespan
so it is necessarily uh more focused
than that uh and uh IT addresses a
specific problem uh we're trying to uh
we're trying to model so um I guess uh
it's
not uh a prorally it's it's not
something a priori uh and it isn't U any
prerequisite to um model uh any
situation but uh when it comes to
how an agent acquires those uh initial
learnings those initial States well
obviously there are many many ways to uh
address that uh problem U with with
various perspectives but
um of course F or active inference uh in
my opinion is not um a theory or a
framework that can answer every um every
question regarding uh to the behavior of
the agent uh in every possible situation
so we need to look for uh other or other
granular problems um in order to uh
account for the lifespan experience of
an
agent got it uh thank you
so um just to kind of reiterate and
clarify this your response for myself um
in my mind I kind of related a bit
to on the one hand this distinction we
we often need to make and keep in mind
between an uh a realist interpretation
of active inference and an
instrumentalist one uh where the latter
is us taking this this mindset of like
okay uh there there are agents out there
in the world there are things out there
in the world and and they do stuff uh we
can't be completely sure of exactly what
they're
implementing uh mechanistically but but
we can develop a framework for uh making
some SE sense of it for ourselves and
part of the way that we make some
progress on that uh making sense project
is to use our own um suspicions use our
own uh Paran knowledge to to write down
or Express or postulate some some
structure to postulates some generative
model uh and then we can we can active
reference as a template where we can
input that generative model uh perform
inference on it and then uh perhaps
eventually make some
predictions um about the behavior of a
system and compare that to to what the
system is actually doing but but what
you're uh something that you're pointing
out is that within the context of the
framework uh there isn't necessarily
some
uh uh procedure
for figuring out okay if you didn't have
this uh these priors about what what it
is that the generative model could look
like uh and
and I suspect ECT we suspect that uh for
example humans don't come with all of
the the structure that they need uh
embedded from the moment they're born in
order to
model uh the world maybe they have some
structure built in but they they acquire
more of it and learn more of it over
time um but active reference is is not
doesn't have all the tools um to
to perform that learning of the
structure you that's also an area of of
work
that's you can do but it's
not
explicitly part of active
ref uh just to clear up a little bit um
here because you see even in the the
very fabric of the first principles of
active inference namely the free energy
principle so the free energy principle
uh assumes the existence of quote
unquote things and then try to
characterize what would the existence of
those things constitute okay so it it
doesn't necessarily uh provide an
account for uh I mean uh how the
existence occurred how how I mean how
how those emergent uh properties arise
from um from from lower causalities
of course it can describe uh those
causal Relationships by assuming that
those uh uh emergent phenomena uh have
happened uh already so uh it takes as
very first as the very first step and as
an initial uh as an initial U State the
very existence of those things right uh
so when it comes to uh Pro U modeling um
an agent's Behavior within active
inference framework I believe the same
mindset applies uh here as well so uh it
doesn't necessarily account for the uh
how questions
but rather to um it it tries to
characterize the what
questions uh I'm not sure uh if it
clears up the I mean your question here
or not but
um it's it's not an account for
um it's not an account that uh tries to
uh let me put it this way um
if if we have this system at our
disposal uh that we we try to understand
um the its mechanism or or um the way it
behaves active inference provides uh a
comprehensive tool
to uh write down uh the behavior of the
agent uh within specific uh mathematical
technology but it doesn't necessarily
account for the um emergence of that
agent it doesn't necessarily account for
how that agent uh emerged at the first
place uh so that's uh one of the
misconceptions about free energy
principle and uh active inference
because some people uh think that uh
free energy principle being the theory
of every quote unquote thing would
necessarily entail uh accounting for the
emergence of uh those ontological
entities uh but uh it it's it was never
uh the claim of free energy principle so
um yeah it takes as uh it takes the
existence of those things um as the
given and then try to describe those uh
Behavior thank you um inks then
Andrew hi I have a separate question but
now I got involved in this so but I do
want to understand so if we were to
model like super deep thick temporal
modeling of a person as they're born and
they go through their life if someone
was sitting there active inferencing
everything that they're doing that would
account for the development of the
faster prior updating of priors and the
slower updating of generative models
right that would somehow build like a
human with their understanding of the
world not build but model how they
become
themselves okay well I mean to to the
coarsest approximation yeah you could
make a generative model that included
decades would that mean it would give
useful insights or interface with
empirical data not not at that course
graining could it be developed to be
richer and more useful and
meaningful interesting question but I
don't know does anyone else want to give
a thought on
that
well I would find it useful I do have
another question though I was just okay
yeah okay sorry so this is um from the
book page
77 um where the figure 44 describes the
basian me basian message
passing
so my question there is the
the black circle
one the one that says intuitively
current beliefs about States under each
policy at each time are compared with
those that would be predicted given
beliefs about States at other
times so this is the the statistician
inferring by comparing different
predicted States at different times does
does that mean is basically time flowing
left to right and you're trying all
these different policy
policies or are these alternative
policies about something you can do
right now and you can do different
things about it and you're trying them
out in your mind is this time
flowing left to right or are these in my
mind like if I do this this will happen
if I do this this will
happen and I compare them in my mind
almost parall like they are
counterfactuals to each
other thank
you yes
Oli uh okay so there's a distinction and
active inference literature between uh
the time as uh t as the letter T and to
so uh more often than not when active
inference researchers use the letter t
for time uh they uh they mean the flow
of time as we know it I mean the
intuitive uh time or our perceived time
but uh what what but when they use to it
doesn't necessarily refer to the flow of
time but rather uh to uh to the steps uh
that an agent uh would take in order to
achieve a goal so uh to in a spec in a
particular moment is not necessarily uh
uh I mean
the time interval between two tows are
not necessarily equal right so uh it it
tries to uh model the specific steps of
uh the decision making or the action
taken uh to achieve a particular
goal thank you that's one aspect I think
there's does anyone else want to give
another thought on this and I clarify my
question is are there counterfactual
policies that only one will get
implemented or is it step after step of
of enacting like a project of long a
strategy of many
policies
so in the pseudo code usually as
implemented during the
policy updating so going from the policy
prior to the policy posterior that's
using the expected free energy so that's
when different policies are being
considered so policy however long it is
it's going to start with your next
action and then include that many steps
out so then if there's you know four
options at each step four affordances so
you're going to do policies of step two
so there's 16 so then in the pseudo code
it would have there's 16 policies and
then there's the prior so if they're all
equally likely then they be all even
then all of them are iterated over in a
loop and then while each one's getting
iterated over it is rolled
out and then then they're all compared
at the
end resulting in the
updated
distribution and then so let's just say
it's it's um 80% for the first option
and then 10 and then five then then a
few so then you could draw from that
distribution and choose to do that or
you could pick just like the best option
which is actually something that um
Magnus discussed in
this uh live stream
55.1 which is about this message
passing because like there there it's
kind of a lot to it but also it's a very
important relationship and also one
that's not really addressed in the
textbook just a few times kind
of dropped
in uh okay Andrew and then anyone
else yeah I just wanted to give my stab
at uh the prior question um it seemed to
be asking what active or the free energy
principle is or isn't and um me it it's
a set of constraints it's it's telling
you what open functions and Funk do
namely your C's your Q's if I am correct
um can and cannot do if they are to be
an entity that persists spatial
temporarily um so it it doesn't tell you
what those functions are they it leaves
them as three variables but it
constrains their behavior
so so it I guess it's a different way of
thinking about things than um thinking
about like what is force equals
masstimes
acceleration it's not showing transfer
of energy it's saying where energy is
constrained to go if something is to
persist over
time
yeah that's very interesting um also
this this is one one paper the title
kind of summarizes this very simple yet
perplexing argument by axal
constants it's not about what it takes
it's about what took you
there
so it's pretty interesting um
ra yeah can you elaborate what's uh your
interpretation of that title
is of what is of this title it's not
about what it takes it's about what took
you
there I think here is said really well
um so just to to generalize it um if
something exists right now under the
right conditions it's because it's done
something like minimizing its free
energy so it's as if it's
used variational free energy however the
question of whether it will exist
tomorrow cannot be settled purely by
resorting to the fact that it will
minimize its free energy to get
there so something could
just all just you know it's I I don't it
may also be like saying um like past
results is not future performance or
something like things could change in
the
niche so it's
it including it minimizing free energy
right to the
end so there's kind of a few other
aspects but but
um yeah and and related to as Oli
mentioned earlier like conditioning on a
thing
existing by by choosing that kind of
boundary of framework then there's
questions that aren't being addressed
and ones that are but yeah right so just
to clarify my original
question
um so definitely we in order to be able
to apply any of this uh of these ideas
we take for granted we take as uh as
assumed the existence of mar conf BL kit
which is what gives our definition of a
thing um my question is about uh so
already assuming that a thing exists and
it has its its
boundary uh
internally it is
representing is encoding some uh model
of the generative process that's going
on
outside uh in the world and it um uses
perception and action
to um make sure that that model is as
consistent as possible with its
observations
um in the world so my question is about
what's inside that generative model um
for example in the case of a pomdp which
is one way of uh
representing uh a discreet time
generative model uh there's some
structure to what that PP looks like the
way that we write it down and what what
are the parameters um and I need to
become more familiar with with the
actual degrees of freedom so to speak
the different things that you can uh add
or or take away to construct a different
varieties of of of a model but but let's
just take that
PDP um
category as an example and the way that
I am thinking about it right now what
what you have is as
you're um incorporating this this
generative model
you have some parameters and uh over
time you update the parameters of
through perception you update the
parameters of that generative model to
be more consistent uh to to reduce uh
your free energy to minimize your free
energy but my question is about the the
the structure of that generative model
not just the the parameters but for
example if uh if it's a a basan network
um that is describing the causal links
between some uh hidden variables some
causes leading causes in the world and
like the observations that you're
receiving that basan network has some
structure there are different nodes and
connections between that and uh somehow
you have to figure out what should that
uh Network look like uh should the
connections between nodes be and what
should each node
represent um and and so I'm
wondering if within the context of
active inference there
is uh there's a procedure there is
procedure for
exploring uh that structure or for given
a thing that already exists how does it
the its generative model evolve not only
in terms of its
parameters uh but more
um uh generally in terms of its
structure maybe this is related to the
idea of hierarch models which uh I
haven't uh learned much about yet
but yeah maybe I hope that to Claris
applies a bit more my question yeah two
short answers first there's structure
learning that is the whole question of
modeling
and that that's what the question of
modeling is
that's why it's just not done just by
thinking about it because you have to
fit the base graph to be capturing
whatever factors you're
modeling but also this paper and some
other ones in that area approach the
structure
learning and also um in live stream
54 with the learning structure versus
structure
learning discussion that that um Toby
uses excellent thank you did you link
these somewhere um uh yeah just in in
where the notes are the notes for
chapter four four thank you so much yeah
all right any other like thoughts on
four or some section that some one found
interesting
if uh no one else has a question about
four I have a question
about uh inference algorithms but but I
want to give everyone the chance
to to ask your
questions
does anyone have like any overall
thought on for yeah okay
Andrew sure I I was still kind of
reflecting on the the question earlier
about message passing I feel like I'm
going to mix some things up here but so
that's back on figure 4.4 and I was just
thinking about the question of
counterfactuals
um because I mean if um if an agent were
to and you'd have to of course like
model them you'd have to construct them
in such a way that they were able to
engage in planning which I suppose would
involve minimizing expected free energy
G um so in that in that case whenever
one is engaging
in you know planning if we could model
that um then I guess is someone I mean
they'd be comparing counterfactuals in
that case right they'd be comparing
different potential policies that they
have not already engaged in or or
potentially are already underway um in
some way but like you know maybe you're
so far along the way and your series
sequence of actions associated with a
particular policy or you haven't started
it yet and then from there the idea is
you would go with the policy that has
the
highest probability is it right you You'
basically you'd go with the policy that
minimizes expected free energy which
would also like whenever we look at that
in terms of a distribution over policies
it' be the policy that has the highest
probability which you end up necessarily
going for um I'm just trying to because
I'm slowly learning how important it is
to specify when you're modeling like all
these factors and things can get a
little blurry whenever we start speaking
a little bit more philosophically or
from real life experience I'm just I
don't know if all of that made sense
right but U just throwing that out
[Music]
there just a quick uh
clarification
question uh you brought up
contrafactual in relation to action
planning and then uh Daniel wrote down
here planning considering future times
steps is all
counterfactual uh what that brings to my
mind is that the way
that um we're thinking about inference
sorry planning in active inference is uh
Imagining the
outcomes of different
policies uh and rolling those out uh
into the future and then Computing the
expected free energy over those roll
outs for each
policy um and then you kind of score the
different uh
policies uh according to their expected
free energy and this kind of gives you
uh a distribution over
which uh policy you're you you expect to
take or which policy you believe you're
you're going to take um but but it seems
like you you maybe like you sample from
that distribution so it's not like you
you just uh take
the
um the policy with with the the the
lowest expected free energy if that's
not true please
someone dispel that yeah right yeah all
planning is that's one kind of
counterfactual counterfactual just being
um considering something something that
is not a factual like observable so
anything about the future time steps is
counterfactual um or like alternative
pasts but then considering the future
it's all counterfactuals and then this
is also kind of from figure
5.4 um this is that section of um taking
in habit and then either passing habit
through the PO prior or updating it
according to expected free
energy and then but whether whether
habit has passed through or there's an
update um then the most likely
path results or that distribution is
sampled
from yeah Jesse so these are two yeah
these are two possible
selection uh methods either maximum
um posterior or or sampling those are
two methods of policy selection given a
policy
posterior I guess for me uh what I'm
attempting to do is I mean because quite
frankly it's all a bit over my head but
um trying to pull this back from like a
lot of this conversation
you know we're we're trying to apply
this to conscious processes which I
think makes it a little bit more
difficult in some respects because
there's so much you
know philosophical baggage um and so in
the last section of this chapter even
though I don't really understand the
application of like the um no I'm sorry
it wasn't the Lan uh approxim yeah the
leace
approximation uh on same motor reflexes
and trying to think about this like even
thinking about the mo the message
passing
framework uh in a purely physiological
Paradigm where the message passing is
say you know the
sensory response from the you know the
doctor hits your you know under your
knee with a little rubber hammer and
either you're going to have a reflex
response or you're not right and so in
that in that respect if I try to look at
the the counterfactuals or the policies
not as
some you know
conscious
um process but as a purely phys excuse
me my throat but is a purely a
physiological
one it just kind of I think for me makes
it a little bit and maybe I'm on the
wrong path and just Mis misunderstanding
it but for me it's just making it a
little bit
uh more simplistic I guess to to deal
with uh all the all the symbolisms and
the idea of gradients and the idea of
it's not like we're consciously always
doing this and and you know undergoing
the statistical process but this is you
know essentially a way of understanding
the probability that you know given
certain factors and
parameters you know your knee gets hit
with a little rubber hammer and you or
you don't so I guess I just want to kind
of throw that out there
for possible
Direction yeah I mean it it's very true
and relevant that that not not
everything Maps or just people may have
wildly different maps of what features
or psychological experiences they map to
like different intuitions about these
Concepts so it's a huge
space um Andrew then
raw um I I don't want to be redundant uh
Daniel pretty much summed up my point
but it's yeah I think it's more about
just thinking about it as far as like
you're a like take the perspective of
someone who's modeling um think of like
you could produce a model of like a
person or or some other phenomena
whatever agent you're looking at and you
could include planning as like an entire
sort of Dimension so to speak or or
layer to your model but that could just
entirely be forone I imagine most people
who are trying to model you know uh
reflex arcs and looking at yeah the
movement of joints in response to you
know the pressure at this particular
spot probably from an active inference
approach I imagine would not include
planning in the modeling process
meanwhile of course if you're trying to
model someone thinking and you know
Consciousness or however close you want
to come to that I think last week we
discussed the the neurop phenomenology
paper I could drop a link to that again
but like that kind of modeling certainly
you could you could include planning as
um as a dimension and and I bring this
up again because it's just that's what
I'm slowly learning with active
inference is like while I enjoy the
philosophical discussion I think it's
super important to just think about like
from a modeler's perspective even though
that kind of like can remove some of the
magic of of the process but it's um it's
you choose what you're going to include
or not include in the model I suppose
right um I think I I just hope that that
clarifies anything it was clarifying to
me to start to understand
that yeah just to connect to um Thomas
pars guess
stream um and like a little bit of the
development of different generative
models because chapter 4 is where the
generative models being described seven
and eight will go into more detail into
the discreet and the continuous time but
chapter four is kind of like just
considering generative models um
generally so the early implementations
were in continuous
time then people were thinking about how
to get sequential
Dynamics that's discussed in this
textbook with these Predator pre type
models so that is like where there was
repetitive curse of
writing so it was
doing like repetitive
structures but it was in a continuous
State space of time um then they started
going more into the explicit
planning explicit like the pdps kind of
tying back to the earlier discussions
that we had so
um and
then later um The Continuous models were
used at the more like sensory motor
layer and then the discret state space
models at higher levels of
decisionmaking
just want to make that point Thomas
explains more but
yeah any any other like thoughts on
four yeah I'd like to um chime in just a
bit
um
so I think it's worth noting
that you this whole active inference is
um is still very much in its
infancy and you there's a lot to work
out I mean you know when we talk
about
um and you to Jesse's point is that you
there there is no Authority here I mean
we're talking about how humans model
their
lives and so
um the assumptions that not only the
modeler has but also the person has is
going to um you know bear on the
counterfactuals and so you know to
produce a model of a person you know we
can't
really discount the fact that what
they're perceiving is not
reality
so I hear a lot of it assumptions that
so I I question these assumptions and
maybe it's because I'm coming out of
worldly mapping but you there's just a
lot of assumptions that you bring up
questions for
me um as to the accuracy which is yeah
the intent of the whole project is
to become more
accurate thank you
Susan one approach there because I I I
really agree with with a lot of what you
raised um by using similar terms and
just being clear about what terms we're
using then some Expressions can be
evaluated and then and just sort of like
very carefully
understood and then different people may
still make different claims about the
same topics C certainly that's what
discourse
is right that's a very
interesting aspect of this poort and The
Institute more broadly which is as I
mentioned Susan this is
very um stof thee art like a young young
kind of
project um
and The Institute is part of the group
of people who like everyone here in
trying to understand the framework is
participating in developing it and
carrying it Forward uh but also
something that's I know that the
Institute is really um working on uh and
keeping in mind is how to to
optimize uh this process of of doing the
science of thinking about the ideas
uh collectively and as Daniel just
mentioned part of that is uh to the
extent that we uh engage with each other
more often and have these discussions
together uh and use um the most precise
language that we can the
ontology uh and become more familiar
with the ontology then we start to
become kind of like uh almost to
approximation uh I have like a
mathematical uh approach to thinking
about it because in math you have very
clear definitions about uh for
everything that you're working with so
so this is very helpful that um that
we're we're becoming more familiar with
the concepts and the terms and then
using them um in a shared way in a way
that hopefully makes sense to as many P
people as possible in every
session but it's also really excellent
to have people who um are maybe less
familiar with some of the technical
details because uh then you can stop uh
others and say like hey that's um isn't
completely clear to me or I'm thinking
of it from this more intuitive
perspective can you um explain how my
intuition laps into
your to the terms that you're
using yeah thank you um Andrew
yeah quick follow on to that point um I
was hoping the ontology on our um uh
what do you call it our epistemological
space had a lookup table for the um
equation
symbology and I didn't find that but
it'd be really helpful if there was like
a word
or something I can do for lookup
card to um help embed that antology uh
built into the active inference
textbooks uh equation into my
brain H it's a great idea it's
definitely something we've considered um
there's several steps that we know we'd
have to do so like in our literature
analysis from the end of
2022 we annotated the number of
equations in each paper for for several
hundred papers obviously we have that
information for textbooks so determine
where the equations are then just like
we have for um some of the equations but
not all of them um develop the natural
language descriptions using the ontology
terms that natural language description
would be including all of the terms that
you need to include make the mapping
between the symbols and the ontology
terms I mean it's a project that that
the
ontology will include and other features
pending
slash people who want to do
it thanks for pointing that out yeah but
it would be epic and and if you want a
sub page or if you want a form to do it
in let's figure out how to do
it
yeah
Susan
um so if I'm premature in asking this
question just you know just say so and
we move on but before equations would
become accurate wouldn't wouldn't it
be um a matter of um pattern languages
that
would be more of a broad scope to be
able
to um you
know audit the equations
Spa that's a very interesting
question
[Music]
um
yeah lot lot of ways you could say it
the equations are being evaluated
according to kind of standard math so if
we consider that as a pattern language
like math is a pattern symbol
set then and also the equations
equations are
usually trivially
true because it's they're codifications
of assumptions basically yeah they're
manipulations of of what is brought in
to the
formalism right so then that has a
certain epistemic status it's not
nothing there are theoretic iCal and
mathematical findings that that are they
are real
findings but that that doesn't justify
or or imply direct application of to
anything of of
anything okay thank
you yeah the on like making it more like
a living textbook with rendering
um equations with the natural language
or change making the variables
compatible or using the computer
variables
um those could help a lot otherwise
there's a lot of variability in which
notation are used and to what extent
notation is
described like hopefully to a limited
extent in a
textbook but still there's a lot of
notation in the textbook and it it kind
of like shifts among the CH the chapters
just bringing in more variables not
necessarily like using one core set of
variables which would be hard to do but
that's not what they
do so one more
question since we're at the top of
the um would it be premature to um
announce that we're we have a special
guest that might challenge our
assumptions on um
physics
Daniel I
[Music]
mean we'll we'll announce it when it's
organized but yeah that sounds
good anyone like have any thoughts on
chapter 4 or like or what they want to
ask about next
week
anyone have any other thoughts on four
yeah
inks I just want to say I love this
equ they're not equations but the ones
that look like waterfalls that go in
different patterns it's very inspiring
to see them and just to Express
gratitude for you guys you are Saints to
do this with us to just sit here Daniel
and try to figure out what the hell I
mean when I say that and want to help us
understand like I don't know that you
guys get enough appreciation and
gratitude so just saying
that
thank
you yeah it's awesome that people come
out and and care and it's interesting
topics and even without even
understanding only at this level of
zoomed
out it's still is pretty
cool I want to second that thank you
Daniel yeah thank
you 100 % it's amazing all you
guys yeah everyone updating generative
models learning about
it we can only do like the tiniest
amount in the synchronous times but you
know
yeah okay cool see you all next time for
part two on chapter four
thank you everyone great to see bye bye
bye